All right, welcome back.
We are on the next lecture, which is actually a continuation.
We're doing kind of a multi-part thing here.
And so what we've been talking about is complex impedance.
So we've been talking about capacitive reactants, and we've been talking about inductive reactants, and then resistance, and then putting it all together and having this thing that we're calling impedance.
And so
Let's just jump right back into where we were.
So what we want to do now is we are going to do an RC circuit.
We're going to do an RL circuit.
And the plan is, and we'll see how this goes time-wise, but what I want to do is I want to do an RC circuit, do a analysis, and then simulate it maybe, and then build it on the bench, and then do the same thing for an RL.
So we've got both examples.
And then we're done with this lecture right here.
All right, so let's go back and let's talk about what we've been doing here.
All right, so let's write some things down.
So the first thing is, and so I'm gonna go a little bit quick here, as if I don't always go quick, but so let's start off and let's write a couple things.
So if we have a capacitor, all right, and a circuit C, and if we have an inductor L, we learn that
the capacitive reactance, which we call X of C equals one over two pi F C, which is equivalent to one over omega C, where omega is the angular frequency.
But we also learned that in reality, if we want to generalize this to impedance, then there's a imaginary term here that goes along with this.
So if we want to write this
in terms of impedance, then we would say Z sub C equals zero plus, and then here was the tricky part, it's one over two pi F C, and then there's a J down here in the denominator.
But remember, we learned that J, and here's some of the imaginary number stuff, remember,
imaginary numbers.
And so electrical engineers, so EEs, call it J, and mathematicians call it I. Alright, either way it's the same thing.
So I squared equals negative one, and of course I equals the square root of negative one.
We also learned that one over I is equivalent to minus I.
Alright, and then J and I of course we can just replace.
So we're gonna, you know, sometimes I will accidentally do both, but J is kind of what we're going to use.
So this right here, we can rewrite this as Z sub C equals 0, excuse me, minus J over 2 pi F C. Or we can leave it in terms of X sub C, and we can say this, we can say
Z sub C equals 0 minus J times X sub C. Alright, so that is the capacitive, this is the impedance and then here's the capacitive reactance.
So this is the total impedance.
Notice it has no, it has 0 for the real part and then it has X sub C for the reactive part.
Alright, which is what we expect.
Now over here on the inductor we've got X sub L equals 2 pi
FL.
All right.
So the inductive reactance is 2 pi FL.
But in reality, and of course that's also we can say that's omega L, right?
If we want omega, which is just 2 pi F, and that's in radians per second, that's the angular frequency.
And again, if we want to generalize this to impedance, right, we say Z sub L equals zero, because there's no real part, it's completely reactive.
And
there's a J up here, so this is plus J two pi FL, which is also equivalent to, we could also just say zero plus, we could say J omega L, and then we could also just put it back in terms of X sub L, and we could say X sub L, and then put a positive J out in front of it,
All right, so once again, let's write this Z sub L equals zero plus J X sub L, and then Z sub C equals zero minus J X sub C. All right, so those are the impedances.
And then if we have a resistor, what's that?
What's its impedance?
Z R equals simply R plus zero J. It has no imaginary part.
So those are all the impedances.
And remember impedance is the,
AC resistance, you could think of it's the resistance in AC, and to keep track of the phase angle, we use this notational trick where we use imaginary numbers because they represent two axes, an X and a Y axis, and the X axis is real and the Y axis is imaginary.
All right, so we remember all that hopefully, so let's just erase that.
All right, so we are gonna jump right in and let's do a, let's do a RC circuit and let's analyze it.
using impedance, complex impedance, and we're going to keep track of all the phasors, either in rectangular or polar form, whatever is convenient for us.
Okay, so let's do this.
All right, so let's make a circuit here, and we're going to have an AC source.
And so we're going to try and simulate this.
So we want stuff that we can kind of simulate.
So we want to be careful what value, excuse me,
We're going to simulate it, that's easy, but we're going to build it also.
So we want to use values that we can actually build and nothing's going to explode or blow up.
So just for now, we'll say that this is a 10 volt source, a 10 volt AC source.
And for now, we'll say, let's just say it's at 50 Hertz.
That's easy enough to change because we're going to use a signal generator.
All right.
And then remember this 10 volts, when we're talking about the 10 volts, we,
And we're talking about sine waves, always about sine waves.
We need to say, is this the peak value or the RMS value?
All right.
So either way will work.
So for fun, we've always been saying this is RMS.
So why don't we just say it's the peak value right now?
And all that means is everything will be in peak values.
All right.
Okay.
So now let's put a resistor.
And let's put a capacitor.
All right.
And that's it.
And then, so we've got our R, we've got our C, and let's set some values here.
So for a resistor, let's see here.
What do I want to use?
Why don't we use 100 ohms?
All right.
And for the capacitor, let's use 10 microfarads.
And again, I like to do things in real time.
I don't like to fake it.
So I don't do these problems beforehand.
You're doing it with me for the first time.
So that way I keep it honest and it, you know, I'm not making things look easy that aren't easy.
So if we get stuck and the numbers don't work out, they just, you know, they're not working out good because we pick bad values.
In a math class or an EE class, values will be picked to make the problems work out easy, and I don't really like that because then it doesn't kind of show what happens.
Now, even though 100 ohms and 10 microfarads are kind of easy numbers, we could pick, you know, definitely worse resistors and capacitors, but still, because we've got pi's in there and two's in there and different things in all these formulas, things get kind of ugly, but that's good.
All right, so we know that we're gonna get a current in here,
right?
And the current's going to go this way and then it's going to flip back and go that way, right?
So we're going to call that current, let's call that current I, all right?
And let's go ahead and just to make this easy, let's call this, actually, yeah, we'll call that I and we'll call that V, V for the source there.
Okay, so let's start writing stuff down here.
So here we go.
All right, so X of C,
All right, the capacitive reactance equals what?
It equals 1 over 2 pi fc, which equals 1 over 2 pi, frequency is 50 hertz, and c is 10 microfarads.
Okay, so that's that right there.
We'll figure what the actual value is in a second.
All right, let's do x sub l. All right, what does that equal?
that equals, oh, excuse me, we don't need an X of L here.
All right, in this case, we just have an R here.
All right, so now let's go ahead and let's start writing down some impedances.
So if we wanna write down Z sub C, it has no real parts, so that's zero.
And then we gotta be careful, it's capacitive, so it's minus J times whatever this X of C is, right?
Minus J times X of C.
So that's zero and then J times, and let's figure out what X of C is, get your calculators out.
Again, I want you to be just super comfortable using a calculator and getting these values and not just thinking you're doing it.
So we put all that in and then we get a value.
So 318, 318.
And what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna go to a frankly,
To make this simple, I am going to round all values to a whole number.
So this is 318.3.
I'm just going to round it to 318.
So this is going to be 318.
This is going to give us a little bit loss of precision, but it'll give us less gray here.
So that's that answer right there.
And then you might see this as simply as minus J318.
That's exactly the same.
We don't have to write the zero here, but it helps us as a placekeeper.
Now, let's do our resistor.
All right, so we wanna figure out what ZR is.
Okay, so that was the whole calculation of X of C. And then if we want ZR, go ahead and we can put this in a different color.
So ZR, all right, equals, it only has a real part, which is 100.
So this is 100.
And then it has no imaginary part.
So we could say plus J zero, all right, or zero J.
All right, so that's it.
So now we've got our two impedances, our two complex impedances, Zc and Zr, all right?
And so now if we want here, we can go and let's go draw these.
All right, real quick.
So let's go on our phasor diagram here, and we could draw these.
All right, and so we know
And we're going to kind of, we're going to overlay, what we're doing here is we're overlaying the imaginary and real axis here.
So there's the plus real axis and the minus real axis would be in that direction.
And then up here would be the plus J axis and here would be the minus J imaginary axis.
All right.
Okay.
So let's go ahead and we'll draw the resistance.
We'll draw its impedance in green here.
So it's impedance is just 100, and it's on the real axis, so ZR.
So if we come out here, and again, these are not to scale, unfortunately.
So that's ZR right there.
And it's completely real, that's why it's on the real axis there.
It has no imaginary component.
And then in red, actually in blue, let's draw the capacitive, let's draw the impedance due to the capacitor, all right?
So the impedance ZC due to the capacitor, now remember, it's always pointing down because it's minus 90 or it's minus J. That's that minus J right there.
See that?
That's that minus J. So it's pointing down and it's 318.
So it's actually much longer.
So just, you know what, just for fun, just for fun, let's kind of make this a little bit to scale.
Let's erase that.
And let's lengthen this up a little bit.
There we go.
Okay.
All right, so this is now gonna be three times as big, right?
So there's one, there's two, there's three-ish.
All right, so there we go.
And let's make this horrible little triangle there.
Okay, arrow.
Okay, and so this is our Z sub C, all right?
And so there are two impedances drawn in this phasor diagram, all right?
So those are correct now,
We could go and we could find the hypotenuse and all that.
We can do it that way, but let's keep working with the complex impedances in the format that they are.
All right, so the first thing is we've got, this is a rectangular form.
So we've got ZC in rectangular form and ZC equals zero minus J318.
And then we've got ZR is 100 plus J zero.
So we've got rectangular form of both of these, right?
Now, can we get the polar form of both of these as well?
So let's see.
So in this case right here, we've got this ZR.
And so if we want the polar form of this, right, that's fairly easy.
ZR equals, and what's the length of this?
Well, if you want to convert from rectangular to polar, we need to take the square root of the square of the real part and the imaginary part.
100 squared, square root is 100.
So when there's only one component, the magnitude is just that one component, right?
So we've got 100.
All right, and what's the phase angle?
Well, here's zero degrees right here.
The phase angle is clearly zero, and we can see that from here.
There's no imaginary component.
If there was an imaginary component, right, that's where that phase angle would come from, but we don't have any.
So the phase angle is zero, zero degrees.
All right, so there's ZR in that format.
Okay, and then ZC.
Okay, let's do that.
So zc again, what's its magnitude?
And be careful here, what's its magnitude?
It's 318.
Its magnitude is 318.
And again, how do we find that?
We square that, and we square that, and then we take the square root of the sum, and since this is zero, minus 318 squared is, and then take, we get rid of the sign when we do that, right?
And then take the square root of that, it's just back to 318.
So it's 318, all right?
And also remember,
These things are all in ohms, right?
So these are in ohms, right?
Ohms, everything is ohms.
All right, so it's, and technically if you, we can put the ohms symbol right there, we could put it after.
So, you know, ohms are there, ohms are there.
All right, and what's the angle here?
So this one is tricky.
So this is minus J. So if there was no angle, if it was zero, it would just be zero degrees.
Minus J is over here, right?
And so minus J is what?
It's minus 90 degrees relative to this X and then plus J, right?
Plus J is plus 90 degrees, right?
So it's minus 90 degrees.
And then also for those of you that don't think in radians as much, right?
So remember there are two pi radians in a circle and that's 360 degrees or
There's pi radians in 180 degrees.
And let's keep dividing pi on 2, 2 in 90, 90 degrees, okay?
So if you can just remember these, 2 pi, 360, pi is 180, and then pi on 2 is 90.
So this is pi on 2, 90 degrees equals pi on 2, and then minus 90 equals minus pi on 2, okay?
All right, so now we've got these values here.
All right, so we've got our complex impedances, both in rectangular and polar form.
All right, and so now let's go ahead and let's write down, let's write down our rule here for Ohm's law.
And our rule for Ohm's law is V equals I times R.
But when we're talking about impedances, now we've generalized this, right?
So now it's not R anymore, it's Z. Okay, so this works all the time, no matter what.
So no matter what, if you have an impedance, a complex impedance, this will work.
And if you just have an R, then there's no complex part of the number, but it surely doesn't hurt to do all the math.
So this formula right here is, you know, Ohm's law for Z. Same thing.
Okay, so V equals I times R.
All right, so let's go ahead and let's figure some things out here.
All right, so the first thing is, why don't we figure out what the total impedance is?
So the total impedance, okay, so let's figure that out.
So if we were to add these two things together, we would call that Z sub T, total impedance.
And just like two resistors, you just add the resistance together, but they're not resistors, they're impedances, they're complex impedances, and we have to add them together using their complex representations.
What are their complex representations?
Well, they're right here.
Here's Z sub C, and here's Z sub R. All right, so when we add these two together, so we're gonna say Z sub T equals Z sub C plus Z sub R. All right, and when we do that, we look at this.
So Z sub C is zero minus 318.
So we can do it like this.
We can say zero minus J318 plus,
z sub r. What's z sub r?
Where'd it go?
100 plus j zero.
And then clearly when you start doing this a little while you realize all you have to do is just kind of overlay the real part here and the imaginary part here because each one is missing the other side.
So
this only has an imaginary part, this only has a real part, so when you add these two things together, it's just 100 minus J318, and there you go, it's 100 minus J318, there it is, very simple.
So it's 100 minus J318, okay?
All right, so that is our total impedance right there.
Okay, so now we have our total impedance, so let's go back over here and
Go back over here.
And so what we want to find out is how about we want to figure out I, and that's going to be V over Z, Z meaning our total impedance.
All right, so first, what is V?
Okay, so this is a, what's V?
Here's V right here.
V is 10 volts, okay?
And, but we need to put this into a complex form, right?
Into complex rectangular or polar form.
So let's, so first,
right now this is the magnitude or it's the peak or RMS and we just said it's the peak so keep that in mind and what we want to do is we want to use the voltage source as the reference for the whole circuit for all the phasors for the current and voltage phasors.
So what we're going to do is we're going to arbitrarily say that
the voltage source has a phase angle of zero and then we'll find everything else relative to that because everything is relative to everything so we can make one the reference, right?
So typically you make the voltage source the reference or you can make the current source the reference also if you had a current source.
We're going to make this the reference.
So V equals 10, right?
And you know it's 10 volts and what's its phase angle?
Zero degrees.
It's as simple as that.
So that's it.
And then if we wanted to put this into
rectangular form, we could do that very easily, right?
So if we want to do that in rectangular form, what's that?
We could also say V equals, the real part is 10, plus zero J. So very easy.
So 10 and zero.
So now, here we go.
So this is 10 volts and zero degrees, right?
Over, what's our Z total?
And we want Z total in, we need it in a polar format, right?
We need in a polar phasor format.
So we need to work on this right here.
So let's do this.
So if we want the length, so here we go.
So if we want the magnitude of ZT, magnitude of ZT, that's gonna equal the square root of 100 squared, right?
Plus negative 318 squared equals, let's get our calculators out and do that.
So we've got 100 squared plus
318 squared, and notice I don't need to put the negative sign in there, obviously it's gonna square out, and then we'll take the square root, and 333 ohms, okay?
333 ohms.
All right, so that's the length, okay, so that's good.
Now what we're looking for is we need the angle.
So remember the angle is the imaginary part over the real part, all right?
So the angle phi is the inverse tangent of the imaginary part,
which is this minus 318.
Minus 318 over the real part, which is 100.
All right, so let's go ahead and do that.
Tangent inverse of minus 318 divided by 100.
We have that right.
Okay, and that's minus 72 degrees.
All right, so
minus 72, and it's 72.5.
So on these values, like I said, we're just kind of rounding a little bit, but on 72.5, since that's right in the middle there, I think I'm just gonna, no, you know what?
Yeah, let's actually, let's just leave that as 72, minus 72.5, because the angle will kind of have a larger effect on things.
All right, so minus 72.5.
Now, is that correct?
Is that correct?
Let's think about that for a second.
So this is a capacitive circuit, right?
A capacitive circuit.
And if we were to add these two reactances or these two complex impedances here together, right?
What would we, what would we do?
We'd kind of put this down like this and we'd go over like that.
And then we'd put the hypotenuse here, right?
And that length, that length, what's that?
Where is that?
That's our 333.
ohms, that's our length, and then this angle, here would be the angle right here, that is that minus 72.5, right?
That minus 72.5 degrees.
That looks about right, even drawn with this horribly incorrect not to scale figure.
So things are doing what they should do, and remember capacitive circuits will have the reactances down
down on the negative imaginary axis, the minus J axis.
So that's why you're getting this negative number here.
Inductive circuits will have the reactants and their complex impedance up on the positive J axis.
So then you're gonna have a positive, right?
And so now we're computing current here.
So let's compute current.
All right, so now we're done here.
We've got this answer down here.
So we want now the phasor here for Z sub T
So what I'm going to do is, can I scooch this in here?
Yeah.
So I'm just going to put this in here.
So I'm going to say Z sub T also equals 333.
And again, we can put ohms here because that's what it is.
And what's our angle?
Minus 72.5.
All right.
So just don't lose that right there.
It's kind of scooched in there.
And OK.
So now we've got everything that we need here.
So now we can put this down here in this denominator.
So we've got 333 ohms, and we've got minus 72.5.
All right, so now let's do this math.
So remember, when you multiply and divide phasors, right, that are in polar format, all we do is just multiply and divide the magnitudes, and then we add and subtract the angles, all right?
When you multiply, you add the angles.
When you divide, you subtract.
So be careful of that.
So first let's figure out the magnitude.
So that's just 10 divided by 333.
All right.
And so we get 0.03.
So why don't we, so we get 30 milliamps right there.
So this is 30 milliamps, we'll call it.
30 milliamps.
And what's its phase angle?
Its phase angle, now we gotta be careful, is zero minus a minus 72.
So it's 72.
72.5 degrees.
All right.
Okay, so it's 72.5 degrees.
Now, that's what I is equal to.
All right, so now we have I, we've got X sub C, we've got Z sub C, we've got Z sub R, we literally have everything in the circuit we could possibly want to know.
So now, let's figure out something else.
What do we want to figure out?
So let's figure out, for example, if we want to figure out what
the voltage across the, what the voltage across the capacitor is.
So if we want to figure out V sub C, let's use a different color for that.
So if we want to figure out V sub C. So V sub C equals, and if we look at Ohm's law here, so voltage equals current times the impedance, all right?
So where and in what format do we want to use?
probably the polar format, because we're doing a multiply here, right?
So let's get the current here, which is 30 milliamps.
All right, so 30 milliamps with an angle of 72.5 degrees.
Okay.
And now we need to multiply that times the impedance of the capacitor, the complex impedance, which is this right here.
All right.
And so that is
318, and hopefully I haven't made any mistakes here.
All right.
And that had a angle of minus 90.
So now let's go ahead and do this.
All right.
So 30 milli times 318 equals 9.54.
So 9.54.
And of course, that's volts and an angle.
What's the angle?
We just add the two angles together, so that's easy enough to do.
So that's 90, excuse me, so that's 72.5 minus 90, and that's minus 17.5, minus 17.5 degrees.
So that's V sub C, all right?
So now we'll get to the significance of that in a second here, all right?
Okay, so let's see here.
Now, how about let's do the same thing.
Let's get a little space here, trying to keep this all on one page.
So, now let's do the same thing for, what are we doing?
For the, for the resistor.
Alright, so let's compute V sub R. V sub R, so is simply the current times the impedance.
Alright, so again, what's the current?
The current is still that 30
milliamps very important the current in the circuit is the current in the circuit always right so keep that in mind the angle is 72.5 72.5 all right and notice i'm putting parentheses here just trying to keep everything straight it's really easy to make a mistake with all this and i probably made one uh but uh hopefully if i did we catch it later uh but uh but just try and keep things as clean as possible all right so we got 30 milliamperes is our current at 72.5 degrees
and now we need our complex impedance for the resistance, right?
And that's right here, right?
And it's 100 ohms at zero degrees, okay?
So that's 100 ohms at zero degrees, all right?
We like zeros.
All right, so now we multiply this together.
So 30 milliamperes, 30 milliamperes times 100, that'll bring us up a little bit.
So we got three volts and,
We've got our angles, so we multiply, we simply add.
Okay, so there is VR.
So there's VR and here is VC, V sub C. All right.
Okay, so now let's look at this for a second.
Let's take a pause here.
We've done a lot of math and hopefully some of it is correct.
So let's take a pause and let's think about what's going on here.
All right, rule number one.
In the capacitor, the voltage and the current are always at a phase, right?
Remember this?
And what is it?
It's ice, right?
So the current leads the voltage or the voltage lags the current in a capacitor by 90 degrees, always.
So this has to be true.
That's number one.
So let's keep that in mind.
Let's see if that's correct.
On the resistor, the current and voltage are completely in phase and the phase angle is zero, right?
Okay.
So let's see first if the voltage and current in the resistor, if the voltage and current in the resistor are in phase, all right?
So what is the voltage of the system?
The voltage of the resistor, here we go, the voltage of the resistor is at 72.5 degrees.
It's three volts at 72.5 degrees, okay.
What is the current in the system?
It's 30 milliamperes and 72.5 degrees.
Okay.
So that checks.
So the voltage and the current are in phase in the resistor.
That's good.
Okay.
And just as a side note, it's actually dissipating real power, right?
And the power that it's dissipating is simply 30 times three, 30 milliamperes times three volts.
So it's actually dissipating power.
That's good.
Now on the capacitor,
What is the current and voltage going through it?
Let's look around here somewhere.
So here's the current.
It's still the 30 milliamperes at 72.5 degrees.
What's the voltage on the capacitor?
Ah, it's over here.
So it's 9.54 volts with a minus 17.5 degrees here.
So wait a minute here.
So minus 17.5 and we've got 72.5.
So let's look at the phaser here.
And I'm just going to draw this on top of this diagram right here.
So bear with me.
So I'm going to use blue and blue is going to be this current phaser.
Okay.
And I'm not going to draw it to scale.
I'm just going to draw it like this.
Okay.
So here is our eye and well, at least I could do for you is I can make this angle more realistic.
All right.
So here is this eye and it says that it's 72.5 degrees.
So this angle right here,
All right, we'll call that like phi one is 72.5 degrees, 72.5 degrees.
Okay, now, where is our voltage over our capacitor?
It's here, and it has a lagging or negative angle of minus 17.5, okay?
So let's go ahead and just draw this in this pink purpley color, minus 17.5.
And again, I'm not doing these things to scale here.
And if I did, this would be huge, because I drew this so big and it's only 30 milliamperes.
But I'm going to draw this kind of small here.
Okay.
And this is V sub C here.
All right.
It's phasor and it's angle.
And what's its angle?
Minus 17.5.
So I'm in the negative direction here.
So this is minus 17.5.
So if you take 72.5 and 17.5, right, and you add up the entire thing, well, look at this.
Look right here.
this is 90 degrees, which it should be, right?
So if we say 72.5 plus 17.5 and the universe is okay, it's 90 degrees.
So this is interesting.
So in the circuit, the rules of the capacitor and the resistor are maintained, but everything's been shifted around, right?
But they're still correct.
And the reason why everything is shifted around, because we've mixed these two components together.
So if this is a purely capacitive circuit, then these angles would be rotated back to zero.
They'd still be 90 degrees, but they'd be rotated back to zero.
The second we add that resistor, we start rotating this phasor relationship.
But for each component individually, the relationship must be maintained, right?
And it is, okay?
So that's it.
So we figured out the current,
We figured out the voltages.
We figured out all the phase angles and that's it.
So we figured out everything, all right?
And so we know everything about this circuit and we can compute what the power is, right?
So the real power here, the only power that's dissipated is in the resistor and it's just 30 milliamperes times three volts, right?
So if we wanted to know that, what is that?
30 exp three, oops.
30 exp three times three is 90 milliwatts.
Right.
So this guy is dissipating 90 milliwatts.
All right.
And and again, we got to be careful with this because this is the peak, not the RMS.
So this is not exactly true because we're not using the RMS values here.
And this is going to be RMS.
So this is kind of the peak power being dissipated.
And then on the capacitor, is there any power being dissipated?
Well,
No, because the current and the voltage are 90 degrees out of phase.
And because they're 90 degrees out of phase, no power can be dissipated.
It's impossible.
They're never overlapping in time, right?
So anyway, keep that in mind.
Remember, capacitors, inductors are reactive.
They never dissipate power.
Real ones do because they're not perfect.
Remember, we looked at the models.
They really have resistors in there and other capacitors and they're not ideal.
Okay, so that's it.
And so,
What I want to do right now is, let's keep going here and we're going to take this circuit and we're going to put it into a simulator, all right?
So let's put this into a simulator.
So let's get that set up right now.
Oh, and before we do that, before we put that into a simulator, on Wikipedia, this is a nice, if you look up phaser,
And I wanted you just to take a look at this, just kind of peruse through this Wikipedia phaser, like a phaser in Star Trek, sort of with an O. It's got some nice, it's got some nice figures here and some nice animated figures, which kind of show you this.
And then it goes through all this math that we've been kind of doing.
All right.
But in a little bit simpler way, this makes it look really, really bad, but this is a nice figure right here showing relationships and so on.
So anyway, take a look at phaser on Wikipedia.
Okay.
All right.
Okay, so what we're going to do here is we're going to use Proteus to do the simulation.
And again, because CircuitMaker does not have simulation, and that's kind of the program that we're going to be using, we're going to be using later when we're laying out circuits.
But for now, we're going to, we're going to use Proteus, which you can download a free copy if you go to the website, which we looked up.
All right.
So here, I've kind of put together a small circuit to kind of mimic what we're doing.
And we kind of use this for some of these experiments that we're doing.
So if we look at our circuit, let's go ahead and we've got 100 ohms here for this R1.
So let's just go ahead and change that to 100 ohms.
All right.
And then for our capacitor, we've got, what do we got?
A 10 microfarad instead, we've got 10 microfarad.
Okay.
And then for our AC source,
We've got AC source and we're doing a peak value here.
And the peak value we said was 10 volts, right?
And the frequency, what did we say is 50 Hertz.
Okay.
And all right.
So when I run this simulation, now a couple of things here, I've got AC volts here.
So this is, and again, this is why this is a great program.
Even if you don't buy it,
because it's fairly expensive.
You get a student edition, it's a lot cheaper.
But even if you don't buy it and you just use the evaluation version, the simulator is worth that alone because you can just drag parts in here and simulate.
It works very, very well, and it does very complex chip level simulation.
So this is great.
So Proteus, download it, and then you can follow along.
And then all I really did here was I went and found these components in the parts libraries, and then you simply
you know, drag them down into the design and then connect up the wires.
And then these AC voltage, AC milliamperes, AC voltage, these are just come down.
And I believe they're right here, these kind of instrumentations, this little instrumentation icon, and then you can grab, you know, different components here, AC voltmeter, AC ammeter, wattmeter, and so forth, and kind of put this together.
All right.
And then this is an oscilloscope, which on channel A and channel B, I'm watching what the AC source is and then watching what the voltage over the capacitor is just for fun.
Now let's go set everything here.
And I've done this a couple of times.
So some of these values will still be here.
All right.
So we have the frequency at 50 Hertz.
And now on this particular simulator, peak means peak to peak.
So I had to remember this actually.
And so that kind of messed things up.
So what I'd like to do is this.
So in our circuit, we were calling the 10 volts, the peak value.
The problem is with that, if we do that and run the simulation, all of these sensors, these instruments to measure currents and voltages work in RMS.
So it's best that we just pretend that everything was RMS, right?
So we'll just say that instead of peak, when we did all the calculations,
it was the RMS value.
It wouldn't change anything.
It's just a convention.
So we're going to say it's RMS volts.
All right.
And we've got 50 Hertz.
So we've got 100 ohms, 10 microfarads.
Let's go ahead and run the simulation.
All right.
We've got our oscilloscope here.
And so we've got all these values and sure enough, they do match.
So we've got 30 milliamps
three volts over the resistor and nine and a half volts over the capacitor.
Let's take a look and let's see if that is accurate.
So we have 30 milliamps.
There's our 30 milliamps.
We have three volts over the resistor and we have nine and a half volts over the capacitor.
So amazingly that is completely correct.
So that's good.
All right, now, so here's the thing.
we have validated the circuit, and so the math matches the simulation.
And that's usually going to be the case.
The math and the simulation will actually be very accurate to each other.
And now, of course, in the simulation, if you have a capacitor that's got a non-ideal model where it has actually some resistance in there and then some inductance as well, that's going to be even a closer model.
But the difference between your math and the ideal model simulated or even the correct model that's not ideal will be very close no matter what.
Where you're going to find a huge disparity many times is when you do the actual build of the circuit.
And this is why there is no, there's nothing like building the circuit.
You have to build the circuit to see how it actually performs.
And the reason why is because the capacitors are not ideal, the inductors are not ideal.
There's all kinds of things going on, parasitic effects that are going on in a circuit.
And of course, when you build something on a PCB, it's going to be much better than if you're building it in solderless breadboard and so forth, but you still want to build it to get an idea of what's going on.
But before we do that, let's take a quick look.
So here's the oscilloscope here and the oscilloscope
of course is, yeah, it's kind of wonky.
I mean, it's a virtual oscilloscope of a virtual circuit being simulated, so we can't expect too much out of it, but it does work.
And so I don't use this that much, but anyway, what we're going to do is we're going to turn the gain up here a little bit so we can see things.
And that's the blue and that's the blue and yellow.
Okay.
And if we look here and follow these leads, the blue signal is the capacitor and the yellow signal
is the source voltage and the blue is the capacitor voltage.
Okay, we see that there is a phase difference between the source voltage and the capacitor voltage.
So the question is, what is it?
Now, I'm sure there's a way to measure it on this tool here somehow, or we could eyeball it.
What we could do is we could get one wave lined up
And then we could change the horizontal sweep rate, the virtual sweep rate here.
Okay, God help us.
So let's turn this down.
All right.
And, all right, so that's not bad.
And then we can slide the position over.
All right, so that's kind of cool.
So we can see where the traces, whoa, whoa, whoa, where the traces cross zero, right?
We could see where the traces cross zero.
And then the yellow is the source voltage,
All right, so there's the yellow, it's a source voltage.
So let's do it a little bit more so that we can kind of see.
All right, so there we know is 180 degrees or pi radians.
We know there's a half cycle.
And there, the yellow trace is the source voltage, and then the blue trace is the capacitor voltage, all right?
So what do we know?
Let's go back and let's look here.
So we see there's a lagging, so we see that
the blue trace, which is the capacitor voltage, is actually lagging the yellow trace, which is the source, right?
So it's lagging it.
So is that correct?
So let's go take a look here.
So if we look up here, it's ice.
So current leads voltage, right?
So that's not helping us too much right there.
But if we go look at the phasor diagram, the voltage phasor is at zero degrees, right?
The voltage phasor is at zero degrees.
And then if we go look at the capacitor phasor,
for voltage, look at that, it's minus 17.5 degrees.
So there it is right there, it's this pinkish one, V sub C. So it's lagging 17.5 from the source voltage, 17.5 degrees.
So that looks pretty accurate.
And so 17.5 degrees right there, and that, you know, looks like to me that's exactly what it is.
So anyway, so the simulation is correct, and that's really cool.
What we would like to do is then go take this simulated circuit and build it and see if the built circuit matches the simulation.
All right, but we're going to have a problem.
And so what I just realized is, well, I didn't realize, I didn't just realize it, but I didn't think about it too hard and I was kind of hoping it would work out.
But the problem is, is that when we run the simulation, we want to use these RMS instruments here.
And to do that, we have to come in here
and we can set what this RMS value is, this peak value, this amplitude value and all that.
The problem is our signal generator cannot do an RMS of 10 volts.
And the reason why is remember, and actually let's bring this up here so we can look at this, make sure we remember this math.
So if we recall, let me get a good color here.
So if we recall,
if we want to compute voltage, RMS, it equals voltage peak times 0.707.
All right, let me do that.
Times, times 707, right?
So the problem is, if based on this right here, if we have a VRMS of say 10 volts equals V peak times 0.707, right?
or the peak equals 10 volts divided by 7.7, 0.707, or multiplied times 1.414.
Let's do that math.
What do we get?
We get 10 divided by 0.707, and that equals 14.14, right?
So the peak equals 14.14 volts.
The signal generator that I have only goes up to a peak of 10 volts.
So we basically can synthesize a sine wave that looks like this, that has a plus 10 and a minus 10.
So we got to kind of work backwards if we want to simulate, you know, build a circuit and simulate it.
So if we had a peak of 10 volts, what would the RMS be?
So RMS is 10 volts times 0.707.
So clearly that's 7.07 volts.
So this RMS would be 7.07 volts.
So we'd have a plus and a minus 7.07 volts.
So if we go back to our simulation and set our simulation for 7.07 volts, and then we run our signal generator at a peak to peak of 10, plus 10 and minus 10, then we should get a matching simulation.
All right, so let's do that.
So let's move this back off here.
And so what we're going to do is we're going to say that we have a RMS of 7.07.
All right.
And now also we can put that there or we can put it in the amplitude and it should end up being 10 and it is it's 9.99.
Right.
And this is I don't like this but if you say peak it really means peak to peak and look at it doubles it.
So it's doing the peak to peak.
So
That can be a point of confusion.
I haven't used this in a while.
And so that kind of confused me for a second, but anyway, let's go back to RMS.
We'll leave it as 7.07, which means we're going to put in an amplitude or a peak voltage of 10 for the positive and a minus 10 for the negative on the signal generator.
Then the simulation will match what we get.
So now we know that our math match the simulation.
So the simulation is correct.
Therefore, whatever we build should match the simulation for a lower voltage, right?
Okay.
So we've got this and let's go ahead and let's run the simulation.
All right.
And everything is working and we've got this two volts and the six volts here and the oscilloscope showing the phase lag and all that.
And then go back here.
All right.
And so we've got our amplitude of 9.99 or 10.
So now what we want to do is let's go to the bench and let's build this circuit.
All right.
And then let's run it and see if we get to these same results.
So we're gonna go and we would just want a 100 in series with a 10 and we want to put instrumentation in here.
So kind of keep a picture of that in your mind and let's go over to the bench and let's build this, okay?
All right, so we've got our board here and let's just put this thing together.
So we need a 100 ohm resistor.
So I've got all my parts here, you can't see them and my wires and everything laid out, so it's easy.
So here's my 100 ohms, that's brown, black, brown, right?
Brown, black, brown.
Let's take a quick look at it on the zoom camera.
There it is, brown, black, brown, okay.
All right, so first thing is we're gonna use, here will be where the signal generator is hooked up.
So here's the signal generator input.
So we're gonna kind of make the circuit exactly how it looks on the screen there.
So let's go ahead and, so the signal coming from the signal generator will come from this top rail.
And there it is right there.
Give ourselves some room here if we want to do anything.
Okay.
And then we're going to have, let's just add a little piece of wire here to put some space between things.
It never hurts to have a little extra space.
All right.
And then we are going to put our capacitor.
So we need a 10 microfarad capacitor.
So here's one right here, 10 microfarad, and this is 63 volts.
So 10 microfarad and 63 volts.
And of course this is electrolytic, so it's polarized.
All right.
And this means it could withstand a maximum of 63 volts.
So when we do that simulation, we want to make sure that we are never exceeding that 63 volts and personally don't exceed it by 50%.
You can probably go 70%.
You can probably go to the whole value, but I would advise against it.
Okay.
All right.
So we're going to put that in there.
And let's, why don't we zoom in a little bit more so you can kind of see a little bit better.
All right.
Okay, so we got those two circuit elements, all right?
And now we're gonna put this one to ground.
This one has to go to ground.
Okay.
So the capacitor is gonna go to ground.
All right, and so now if we turn the signal generator on, this circuit will energize and it'll do what it's supposed to do.
And the couple things that we wanna be careful of is the amount of current
that we're putting through different components of the circuit, like the resistor.
We already computed it's like 90 milliwatts, and this is a quarter watt resistor, so that's okay.
So, you know, do sanity checks as you're building things, so nothing blows up or explodes or whatever.
Again, I'm wearing protection glasses, even though we're not gonna put a lot of power through here.
You got capacitors, you never know, something might pop, so it never hurts to wear protection glasses.
All right, and so now let's add some instrumentation.
So we wanna measure the voltage across the resistor,
the current in the circuit, and the voltage across the capacitor.
So we're gonna add a lot of instrumentation.
We don't wanna put too much load on the circuit.
So for now, why don't we just, let's measure just the two voltages, and we can measure the current maybe after.
All right, so we need to put a voltmeter across the resistor, across it, not from here to ground, not from here to ground, but across it, and then across the capacitor.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna get a couple wires,
And we're going to go across the resistor differentially.
And then we're going to plug in one of these little guys that I made out of these power supply connectors.
These PC power supply connectors.
These are really, really, really, really, really useful.
All right.
And the probes will go in there.
So there's that one voltage.
Now let's get the capacitor.
The capacitor to ground is the next voltage that we want to monitor.
So let's get another wire here.
And we want to put it at the top.
And why don't we put it right here?
Don't want to get too messy.
And then maybe we can do a, do we have a shorter one?
Not really.
All right.
So then, and I know that the connections are three, three holes apart or 0.3 inches.
This is 0.1 inch spacing.
All right.
So I just put those three apart and then I'll put this in here.
And again, orientation doesn't matter because we're measuring AC.
Right?
We're going to measure AC signals.
Now, the meters, here's another potential problem.
The meters are going to measure, what are the meters going to measure?
The meters are going to measure RMS values if they are an RMS meter.
And you want what's called a true RMS meter.
And what that means is it doesn't assume the signal is sinusoidal and just look for peaks and then synthesize a sign mathematically and then do the math.
it actually digitizes the signal.
So it actually is measuring the signal.
So if it's a deformed sign, it'll be correct.
So anyway, that's important if you wanna do very accurate voltage, current and power calculations with your meters, you want true RMS meters, all right?
Okay, so what we're gonna do is we're gonna hook these two meters up and then I'm gonna try and get everything on the screen here.
So I'm gonna hook the meters up.
So let's see here.
So the voltage over the capacitor, how about this?
The voltage over the resistor will be the big green meter.
So we're going to do that, big green meter.
Okay.
And that'll get on screen in just a second.
And it's always fun trying to get everything to fit here.
So I'm going to zoom out a little bit here.
All right.
Okay.
So there is our big green meter.
All right.
And I'm going to zoom out some more.
Okay.
Don't worry about the camera shake.
I'll stop it.
All right.
And then we're, we've got this black meter here.
And so first let's get both of these things to turn on and we'll turn this one on.
All right.
Make sure it's an AC mode.
And the range is correct.
Okay.
So the black meter is going to be the capacitor voltage.
All right.
Now we're going to see now again,
You know, I like to do these demos, you know, on the fly.
So we're gonna kind of find things out as we go.
And then the reason why is, you know, we're never gonna be surprised and we're not gonna have to figure out any problems.
All right, so I try to just do this as we go so we can kind of, you know, see things go wrong.
Otherwise, we're never gonna learn anything.
All right, so, okay, so I think we're ready.
And all right, so now what we're gonna do is we're going to go on to the,
signal generator, and we're going to set the signal generator so it's plus and minus 7 volts, 7.07 volts, all right?
So again, let me put a camera on that for you.
Okay, so you can see the view of the signal generator, and so now I've got the frequency at 50 Hertz, and I could change it there if I wanted, but it's at 50 Hertz.
And then we've got the amplitude here.
We've got seven volts for the high, and we've got minus seven for the low.
And then you can see the synthesized signal.
It kind of shows you the signal, which is nice.
And we've got a sine wave, right?
We could, you know, there's a square wave, but we want a sine wave because we're doing sinusoids.
And then if we press this button again on this particular signal generator, it'll show you that the peak-to-peak value is 14 volts.
Okay?
So the peak-to-peak value is 14 volts here.
And so what we want here is we want to make this 10 volts, right?
So that we get a 7.07 RMS value, right?
So what we need to do is we're going to drive this thing all the way up to the 20 volts, right?
So we're going to drive this up to, and sometimes it's just easier to enter it in.
Okay.
So now I've got 20 volts peak to peak, so we've got
plus 10 and minus 10, but the RMS value of 10 would be 7.07 and minus 7.07, right?
So back in our simulation, that's what we have.
So now when we run the circuit, we should get something similar to what the simulation says, all right?
So now I'm gonna go ahead and I'm gonna turn this on.
All right, so we go ahead and turn on the,
signal generator, and let's take a look and see what we have here.
So we have 5.98 volts across the capacitor, and we've got about 1.6 volts across the resistor, and that's what this is showing.
And again, these are RMS values.
All right, so we've got about 6 volts and about 1.6.
Now, if we go back and look at the simulation,
The simulation here says that we should have about 6.76 volts and about 2.14 volts, all right?
And about 20 milliamps of current, all right?
So we're in the ballpark.
So we've got six and 1.6 instead of 6.7-ish and 2.1, all right?
So what is wrong?
So what's wrong?
Well, the problem is this capacitor.
This capacitor is electrolytic and it says 10 microfarads on it.
But it's got a tolerance of like 20%.
So it could be 8 to 12 microfarads, right?
So that capacitor is not very accurate.
All right, so we could grab another capacitor.
And again, many types of capacitors, if you want them accurate, the cost goes up dramatically.
The only reason you'd want a very accurate capacitor is because it's in a filtering circuit and you are doing very, very specific filtering.
Otherwise, typically,
It's in a circuit as a bypass capacitor or a charge storage capacitor, an extra 20% either way.
It doesn't matter because you're going to design it so that it's big enough no matter what to do what you need it to do.
But let's go ahead and let's try a different type of capacitor.
So let me show you this in front of a zoom camera.
All right.
So this, and it may not be able to focus on it.
Oh, it can't because of the object in the back.
But anyway, this is a ceramic capacitor.
And this is 10 microfarads.
So what we're going to do is we're going to replace the electrolytic.
So let's go ahead and turn off the signal generator.
I'm just going to replace the electrolytic capacitor with the monolithic ceramic capacitor, meaning it's non-polarized.
Okay, I've replaced it.
Now let's turn the signal generator back on.
And now we've got 6.09 volts and 2.1.
Going back to the simulation, we've got 2.1 and 6.7, right?
So a little bit closer, but we're still off.
So in reality, these capacitors are just not accurate enough to make what we build close to the simulation.
The question is, could we figure out what this capacitance is, at least how it's acting in the circuit?
Sure.
We can go back to the simulation.
And what we can do is we can adjust the simulation.
We're looking for 6.1 and 2.1, 6.1 and 2.1.
We know to start at 10.
So let's adjust what the capacitor is in the simulation to meet what we're finding in reality here.
So 6.1 and 2.1.
All right, so we're back here in the simulation.
And so what we're gonna do is we're gonna stop the simulation.
And this is great.
This is, you know, when you learn is when you see how you have to kind of go to the bench, check things out, you kind of come back.
So let's adjust this and let's just make it nine microfarads.
All right, so let's make the circuit less capacitive and let's run the simulation.
All right, and what are we getting?
We're getting 6.8 and 1.94.
So that looks like we're probably going in the wrong direction.
Let's see, let's go eight and let's rerun the simulation.
All right, and 1.7 and 6.8.
So we're going in the wrong direction, all right, for that capacitor.
So apparently we need to go larger.
So let's try 12 microfarads.
All right, run the simulation.
Ah, okay, so now we've got 6.6 and 2.5.
All right, 6.6 and 2.5.
All right, and so let's go to 11.
All right, and run the simulation.
All right, and now we've got 2.3 and 6.6.
So you can see we're kind of homing in on the capacitor.
But remember, there's other parasitic effects here.
And we have this thing built on a solderless breadboard.
And that's why we're not seeing the system work the way that we think it would.
Now, let's try this.
Let's go ahead and let's increase the frequency.
All right, we'll increase the frequency.
And let's increase the frequency to say 1000 Hertz.
And let's put our capacitor, leave our capacitor at 11 because
That probably is a little bit more accurate to what we are.
All right, let's run the simulation, move the oscilloscope.
So now we've got seven and one volt.
So notice the voltage has changed and kind of switched around, right?
And the reason why is because the capacitor's reactance now, right?
The capacitor's reactance to this high frequency, right?
And if we remember the capacitive reactance, X of C is one over two pi F C, and now F just went up, so the capacitive reactance just went down, all right?
So now we have seven and one volts, which is kind of lucky.
And so now let's go look to the simulation.
Let's run it at a thousand Hertz and let's see what we get.
All right, so we're back over here at the simulation and we're thinking that this capacitor is probably more like 11 microfarads, right?
Somewhere around there.
So now we're gonna go to the frequency adjustment here and then we'll put this to a hundred.
and then we'll move the control to the left here.
Okay, 200, 300, 400, 500, 600, 700, 800, and 1000, or one kilohertz.
Okay, we just changed the frequency to one kilohertz, and I've switched meters here, and the reason why is the other meter, the leads seem to be getting loose inside of the sockets.
All right, so anyway, now looking at these two meters, we see 0.75 volts and 4.5 volts.
Back in the simulation, we've got one volt over the capacitor and seven volts over the resistor.
So let's make sure here what we've got going where here, right?
So the green meter is over the capacitor.
The green meter is over the capacitor and that's 0.75.
And the lime green or bright green is over the resistor and that's showing 4.5 or 4.6.
So we're getting 0.75 and 4.6, whereas in the simulation, we're getting seven volts and one volt.
So this should be one volt, and this should be about seven volts, right?
Again, what's wrong?
Again, what's wrong is, is that the capacitor is not acting exactly as it should.
So it's frequency dependent as well.
So again, you know, we come to the conclusion that not only do all these wires affect things when you're talking about analog signals, right?
The components are not ideal.
And things get affected.
So that's why the way that you build things is very, very, very important.
And how you build them is very important and that you model things correctly and that you test things.
All right.
So we see that as we increase the frequency, this circuit becomes even more and more non-ideal.
Because other things start to come into play.
What comes into play?
Inductance starts coming into play.
High frequencies, inductors don't like high frequencies.
And so that starts affecting the circuit and we start getting impedances.
These wires and all this affect things.
And another thing that affects things is actually having the meters themselves in the circuit.
These are impedances, right?
They're not for free.
We don't just connect them to something, they have infinite input impedance.
They actually have impedance.
So when you connect these to a circuit like this, it actually affects the circuit as well.
So there's that.
So just measuring it affects the circuit.
So that's why you wanna have really expensive meters and really good probes.
And here's a crazy fact.
Really, really good probes, these probes, really good probes can cost up to $10,000 or $20,000 each, if you can believe that.
That is crazy.
You can go on Digikey and Amazon and you can find $10,000, $20,000 probes.
So anyway, so we did the math, we did the simulation, we built the circuit, we adjusted the circuit because our signal generator couldn't go high enough.
Then we've kind of played around with frequency a little bit and we see that, yes indeed,
capacitor acts as a frequency, a frequency dependent resistor, right?
An inverse, all right?
And then just let's watch these two values right here as I change the frequency again.
So I'm going to go over here and I'll turn it to, so right now we've got 0.75 and 4.5 and I'll turn it to 2 kilohertz and you can see it changing, 4 kilohertz, 5 kilohertz.
All right, so we're at the 5 kilohertz.
And we see that this value right here is the voltage drop over the capacitor, and this is the voltage drop over the resistor.
And we see that the voltage drop over the capacitor, right, the RMS value of that, is very, very low as we increase the frequency.
Let's increase it some more.
Let's take it up to 10 kilohertz.
Now it's at 10 kilohertz.
Now it's almost nothing.
So why is that?
Well, the reason, remember, the capacitive reactance goes up as the inverse of the frequency.
So the capacitive reactance is nearly zero.
Let's figure out what it is, right?
It's one over two pi fc, okay?
So two times pi times the frequency, 10 kilohertz, times the capacitance, 10x minus six equals, take the inverse of that, 1.6 ohms.
So this is 1.6 ohms right now because of the frequency.
So again, the higher the frequency,
It acts as a frequency-dependent resistor, an inverse resistor, 1 over R, or 1 over F. So the higher the frequency, the lower the resistance.
That's useful.
Same as the inductor, except the inductor is directly proportional.
The higher the frequency, the higher the resistance.
And now let's lower the frequency back down.
9, 8, 7, 6, 5, and notice the voltage is going up, 1 kilohertz.
Now, 900, 800, 700, 600, 500, 400, 300,
200 100 there's 100 now look we're at 4.77 and the 3.2 volts on the on the resistor all right and then we can go even lower we can go down to like 10 hertz all right and at 10 hertz now we have the opposite
We have everything dropping over the capacitor, 6.97, and very little dropping over the resistor.
All right?
So that's about it.
So that was good.
So let's stop here, and then we'll do another part, and we're going to do an analysis of an LR circuit.
Same kind of thing.
We're going to do an analysis, simulate it, and then we're going to build it.
So go ahead and stop here, and I'll meet you there.